Robert Lansing Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Robert Lansing Papers 1831-1935 (bulk 1914-1920)
MSS29454
Lansing, Robert, 1864-1928
6,000 items
77 containers plus 6 oversize
17 linear feet
3 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer, diplomat, secretary of state during the Wilson administration, and member of the American mission to negotiate a peace treaty following World War I. Correspondence, memoranda, reports, resolutions, desk diaries, book manuscripts, speeches, scrapbooks, clippings, printed material, memorabilia, photographs, and other papers relating chiefly to Lansing's years (1914-1920) as counsel to the Department of State and as secretary of state and particularly to American foreign relations during World War I, the Paris Peace Conference, and Lansing's relations with President Woodrow Wilson and with various foreign diplomats and statesmen.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Anderson, Chandler P. (Chandler Parsons), 1866-1936--Correspondence.; Boyer, Frederick M., 1872-1944--Correspondence.; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925--Correspondence.; Bryce, James Bryce, Viscount, 1838-1922--Correspondence.; Davis, John W. (John William), 1873-1955--Correspondence.; Dickinson, J. M. (Jacob McGavock), 1851-1928--Correspondence.; Dulles, Allen, 1893-1969--Correspondence.; Dulles, John Foster, 1888-1959--Correspondence.; Elkus, Abram I., 1867-1947--Correspondence.; Foster, John Watson, 1836-1917--Correspondence.; Fuller, Paul, -1947--Correspondence.; Gerard, James W. (James Watson), 1867-1951--Correspondence.; Hibben, John Grier, 1861-1933--Correspondence.; Johnson, Cone, 1860-1933--Correspondence.; Jusserand, J. J. (Jean Jules), 1855-1932--Correspondence.; Koo, V. K. Wellington, 1888-1985--Correspondence.; Lane, Franklin K.--Correspondence.; Lansing, Robert, 1864-1928.; Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1850-1924--Correspondence.; MacVeagh, Wayne, 1833-1917--Correspondence.; Marshall, Thomas R. (Thomas Riley), 1854-1925--Correspondence.; Meiklejohn, Alexander, 1872-1964--Correspondence.; Moore, John Bassett, 1860-1947--Correspondence.; Morgenthau, Henry, 1856-1946--Correspondence.; Phillips, William, 1878-1968--Correspondence.; Polk, Frank L. (Frank Lyon), 1871-1943--Correspondence.; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937--Correspondence.; Rowe, L. S. (Leo Stanton), 1871-1946--Correspondence.; Scott, James Brown, 1866-1943--Correspondence.; Smith, Edward North, 1868-1943--Correspondence.; Stone, William Joel, 1848-1918--Correspondence.; Van Santvoord, Seymour, 1858-1938--Correspondence.; Whitlock, Brand, 1869-1934--Correspondence.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924--Correspondence.; Woolsey, Lester Hood, 1877-1961--Correspondence.
Organizations
Lusitania (Steamship); Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920)
Subjects
Diplomatic and consular service, American.; International law.; Merchant marine--United States--History--20th century.; World War, 1914-1918--Diplomatic history.; World War, 1914-1918--Personal narratives.; World War, 1914-1918--Transportation.
Places
China--Foreign relations--United States.; Ireland--History--Sinn Fein Rebellion, 1916.; Japan--Foreign relations--United States.; Latin America--Foreign relations--United States.; Mexico--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--China.; United States--Foreign relations--Japan.; United States--Foreign relations--Latin America.; United States--Foreign relations--Mexico.; United States--Politics and government--1913-1921.; Virgin Islands.
Titles
Robert Lansing Papers: Private Memoranda, Desk Diaries, and Notes at the Library of Congress
Occupations
Cabinet officers.; Lawyers.; Statesmen.
Provenance
The papers of Robert Lansing, lawyer, counsel in international arbitration courts, secretary of state, and member of the American commission to negotiate peace at Paris in 1918, were given to the Library of Congress in three installments in 1929 by his wife, Eleanor Lansing. There were subsequent gifts in 1956 by Emma S. Lansing and John Foster Dulles and in 1980 from the Yale University Library.
Additional Guides
A listing of important topics, correspondence, and events reflected in containers 1-62 in the Chronological File, 1911-1928, is appended to the finding aid in the Manuscript Reading Room.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Robert Lansing are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on three reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Online Content
The Private Memoranda and the Desk Diaries and Notes series are available on the Library of Congress Web site at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/collmss.ms000072.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1864, Oct. 17 Born, Watertown, N.Y.
1886 Graduated, Amherst College, Amherst, Mass.
1889 Admitted to New York bar
1890 Married Eleanor Foster
1892 1893 Associate counsel for United States on Bering Sea fur-seal arbitrations
1896 1897 Counsel, United States Bering Sea Claims Commission
1903 American counsel, Alaskan Boundary Tribunal
1906 Helped found American Society of International Law
1907 Associate editor, American Journal of International Law
1909 1910 American counsel, Hague Tribunal for arbitration of the North Atlantic Fisheries
1912 1914 Agent of American-British Claims Arbitration
1914 Appointed counsellor for State Department
1915 1920 Secretary of state
1917 Lansing-Ishii Agreement
1918 1919 Member, American commission to negotiate peace at Paris, France
1921 Published The Big Four and Others of the Peace Conference. Boston and New York. Published Notes on Sovereignty from the Standpoint of the State and the World. Washington, D.C.: The Endowment.
1920 1928 Member, firm of Lansing and Woolsey
1923 Counsel for China Counsel for Persia
1923 1925 Counsel for Chile in Tacna-Arica Arbitration
1928, Oct. 30 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Robert Lansing (1864-1928) span the years 1831-1935 with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1914-1920. The collection chiefly concerns his service as counsellor for the Department of State (1914-1915) and as secretary of state (1915-1920). It focuses on World War I, Lansing's participation in the American commission to negotiate peace at Paris and the gradual rift between him and President Woodrow Wilson which eventually culminated in his resignation in 1920, the Lusitania affair, the Mexican crisis, the arming of merchantmen, the Irish rebellion, the purchase of the Danish West Indies, relations with Japan and China, and Latin America and the proposed Pan American Pact. Papers of a personal nature concern Lansing's participation in private legal cases involving international law and his activity in domestic politics. The collection is divided into seven series; Chronological File, Private Memoranda, Desk Diaries and Notes, Correspondence, North Atlantic Coast Fisheries, Speeches and Writings, and Scrapbooks.
The Chronological File includes the bulk of Lansing's correspondence as well as memoranda, reports, and other material. The Private Memoranda includes personal accounts of cabinet meetings, character sketches and impressions of men with whom he dealt, and detailed descriptions of the peace conference negotiations in 1919. The Desk Diaries contain notations on Lansing's activities and during periods when he was abroad contain more descriptive and personal entries. The Correspondence series supplements the Chronological File and primarily consists of his letters with Frederick M. Boyer, Miscellaneous correspondence includes some family letters as well as important letters from important individuals. The North Atlantic Coast Fisheries series relates to Lansing's arbitration at the Hague in 1910. The Speeches and Writings contains two drafts of books including War Memoirs of Robert Lansing, which contains material not contained in the published edition as well as speeches and miscellaneous writings. The Scrapbooks cover a wide range of Lansing's activities including his marriage and articles written about him after his death.
Significant correspondents in the papers include Chandler P. Anderson, William Jennings Bryan, James Bryce Bryce, John W. Davis, J. M. Dickinson, Allen Welsh Dulles, John Foster Dulles, Abram I. Elkus, John Watson Foster, Paul Fuller, James Watson Gerard, John Grier Hibben, Cone Johnson, J. J. Jusserand, V. K. Wellington Koo, Franklin K. Lane, Henry Cabot Lodge, Wayne MacVeagh, Thomas R. Marshall, Alexander Meiklejohn, John Bassett Moore, Henry Morgenthau, William Phillips, Frank L. Polk, L. S. Rowe, Elihu Root, James Brown Scott, Edward North Smith, William Joel Stone, Seymour Van Santvoord, Brand Whitlock, Woodrow Wilson, and Lester Hood Woolsey.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in eight series:
Chronological File, 1911-1928
Private Memoranda, 1915-1922
Desk Diaries and Notes, 1914-1920
Correspondence, 1831-1921
North Atlantic Coast Fisheries, 1909-1910
Speeches and Writings, 1891-1935
Scrapbooks, 1890-1933
Oversize, 1890-1933
Container List
- Chronological File, 1911-1928 (Box 1-62)
  Bound volumes containing correspondence, memoranda, reports, resolutions, and other material.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1911, Jan. 31-1913, Dec. 11 (Box 1)
  - 1913, Dec. 13-1914, June 1 (Box 2)
  - 1914, June 2-Aug. 30 (Box 3)
  - 1914, Aug. 31-Oct. 2 (Box 4)
  - 1914, Oct. 3-Nov. 14 (Box 5)
  - 1914, Nov. 16-1915, Jan. 8 (Box 6)
  - 1915, Jan. 9-Feb. 25 (Box 7)
  - 1915, Feb. 26-Mar. 29 (Box 8)
  - 1915, Mar. 30-June 3 (Box 9)
  - 1915, June 4-July 10 (Box 10)
  - 1915, July 12-Aug. 7 (Box 11)
  - 1915, Aug. 8-Sept. 3 (Box 12)
  - 1915, Sept. 4-Oct. 7 (Box 13)
  - 1915, Oct. 8-Nov. 14 (Box 14)
  - 1915, Nov. 15-Dec. 23 (Box 15)
  - 1915, Dec. 27-1916, Feb. 2 (Box 16)
  - 1916, Feb. 3-Mar. 31 (Box 17)
  - 1916, Apr.1-May 18 (Box 18)
  - 1916, May 22-July 6 (Box 19)
  - 1916, July 7-Sept. 20 (Box 20)
  - 1916, Sept. 21-Oct. 31 (Box 21)
  - 1916, Nov. 2-Dec. 5 (Box 22)
  - 1916, Dec. 6-1917, Jan. 23 (Box 23)
  - 1917, Jan. 24-Feb. 28 (Box 24)
  - 1917, Mar. 1-Apr. 3 (Box 25)
  - 1917, Apr. 4-19 (Box 26)
  - 1917, Apr. 20-May 24 (Box 27)
  - 1917, May 25-July 2 (Box 28)
  - 1917, July 3-Aug. 8 (Box 29)
  - 1917, Aug. 9-Oct. 2 (Box 30)
  - 1917, Oct. 3-Nov. 19 (Box 31)
  - 1917, Nov. 20-Dec. 15 (Box 32)
  - 1917, Dec. 17-1918, Jan. 29 (Box 33)
  - 1918, Jan. 30-Apr. 10 (Box 34)
  - 1918, Apr. 10-June 10 (Box 35)
  - 1918, June 11-29 (Box 36)
  - 1918, July 1-Aug. 12 (Box 37)
  - 1918, Aug. 3-Oct. 9 (Box 38)
  - 1918, Oct. 10-Nov. 9 (Box 39)
  - 1918, Nov. 10-1919, Jan. 4 (Box 40)
  - 1919, Jan. 16- Feb. 24 (Box 41)
  - 1919, Feb. 25-May 9 (Box 42)
  - 1919, May 10-June 20 (Box 43)
  - 1919, June 21-July 30 (Box 44)
  - 1919, July 31-Aug. 22 (Box 45)
  - 1919, Aug. 23-Sept. 15 (Box 46)
  - 1919, Sept. 16-Oct. 14 (Box 47)
  - 1919, Oct. 15-Nov. 10 (Box 48)
  - 1919, Nov. 11-Dec. 4 (Box 49)
  - 1919, Dec., 5-23 (Box 50)
  - 1919, Dec. 30-1920, Feb. 10 (Box 51)
  - 1920, Feb. 11-Mar. 31 (Box 52)
  - 1920, Apr. 1-June 23 (Box 53)
  - 1920, June 24-Dec. 3 (Box 54)
  - 1920, Dec. 6-1921, Jan. 31 (Box 55)
  - 1921, Feb. 1-May 2 (Box 56)
  - 1921, May 3-Aug. 11 (Box 57)
  - 1921, Aug. 19-Dec. 21 (Box 58)
  - 1921, Dec. 23-1922, Apr. 15 (Box 59)
  - 1922, Apr. 21-1923, Jan. 10 (Box 60)
  - 1923, Jan. 15-1924, May 5 (Box 61)
  - 1924, May 15-1928, Nov. 28, undated (Box 62)
- Private Memoranda, 1915-1922 (Box 63-64, Reel 1)
  Original and typescript copies of Lansing's personal memoranda and notes.
  Available on microfilm, shelf no. 15,347.
  - Originals (Box 63, Reel 1)
    - 1915-1917 (Box 63, Reel 1)
    - 1918-1919 (Box 63, Reel 1)
    - 1919 (Box 63, Reel 1)
    - 1918, Dec. 4-1919, Dec. 14 (Box 63, Reel 1)
    - 1916-1919, character sketches (Box 63, Reel 1)
    - 1920-1922 (Box 63, Reel 1)
  - Typescripts (Box 64, Reel 1)
    - 1915, Apr. 15-1918, Dec. 30 (Box 64, Reel 1)
    - 1919, Jan. 2-Dec. 27 (Box 64, Reel 1)
    - 1920, Jan. 1-1922, May 23 (Box 64, Reel 1)
- Desk Diaries and Notes, 1914-1920 (Box 65-67, Reel 2-3)
  Bound volumes containing notations and descriptions of days' proceedings.
  - General (Box 65, Reel 2)
    - 1914, Oct. 21-1915, June 8 (Box 65, Reel 2)
    - 1915, June 9-Dec. 31
    - 1916 (Box 66, Reel 2)
    - 1917 (Box 66, Reel 2)
    - 1918 (Box 66, Reel 2)
    - 1919 (Box 66, Reel 2)
    - 1920 (Box 66, Reel 3)
  - South America, 1917 (Box 67, Reel 3)
    - 1 of 3 (Box 67, Reel 3)
    - 2 of 3 (Box 67, Reel 3)
    - 3 of 3 (Box 67, Reel 3)
- Correspondence, 1831-1921 (Box 68-70)
  Correspondence and other material.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and chronologically therein. This series supplements the chronological file.
  - Boyer, Frederick M. (Box 68)
    - 1911-1916, (7 folders) (Box 68)
    - 1917-1918, (4 folders) (Box 69)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 69)
    - 1831-1918, (4 folders) (Box 69)
    - 1921, undated, (6 folders) (Box 70)
- North Atlantic Coast Fisheries, 1909-1910 (Box 70-74)
  Printed and near-print volumes relating to the North Atlantic Fisheries Arbitration at The Hague.
  - British case, 1909 (Box 70)
  - Appendix to British counter case, 1910 (Box 70)
  - Arbitration at the Hague, 1910 (Box 71)
    - Vols. 1-2 (Box 71)
    - Vols. 3-4 (Box 72)
    - Vols. 5-6 (Box 73)
    - Vols. 9-10 (Box 74)
- Speeches and Writings, 1891-1935 (Box 75-77)
  Book manuscripts, speeches, and other material.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and chronologically therein.
  - Books (Box 75)
    - War Memoirs of Robert Lansing, 1935, (6 folders) (Box 75)
    - Principles of American Political Parties, undated, (5 folders) (Box 76)
  - Miscellaneous, 1909-1919, undated (Box 76)
  - Speeches, 1891-1912, undated, (16 folders) (Box 77)
- Scrapbooks, 1890-1933 (Box 77)
  See Oversize.
  - Scrapbooks are located in the Oversize Series (boxes OV1-OV6). See Oversize (Box 77)
- Oversize, 1890-1933 (Box OV 1-OV 6)
  Scrapbooks containing newspaper clippings, programs, letters, invitations, and other material.
  Arranged and described according to the series, containers, and folders from which the items were removed.
  - Scrapbooks (Box OV 1)
    - 1890, Jan. 15-1894, Nov. 29 (Box OV 1)
    - 1914, Mar. 20-June 13 (Box OV 1)
    - 1914, Sept. 2-1915, June 10 (Box OV 1)
    - 1915, June 9- July 13 (Box OV 2)
    - 1915, July 7-1916, May 30 (Box OV 2)
    - 1915, Oct. 13-1921, Nov. 12 (Box OV 3)
    - 1916, Oct. 17-1918, Nov. 21 (Box OV 4)
    - 1918, Dec. 8-1920, Feb. 26 (Box OV 4)
    - 1919, Oct. 30-Nov. 13 (Box OV 4)
    - 1905, June 20-1927, Apr. 6 (Box OV 5)
    - 1920, Feb. 14-1925, Dec. 25 (Box OV 5)
    - 1924, Oct. 11-1928, Mar. 1 (Box OV 5)
    - 1928, Oct. 30-1933, Jan. 16 (Box OV 6)
    - 1917, Apr. 23-25 (Box OV 6)